<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An admonition given unto Mr. Saltmarsh: wherein his great sinne in writing those pamphlets intituled, A new quære, Smoak in the temple, Groanes for liberty, &amp;c. is plainly laid open before him, and charged upon his conscience. Where also among other things spoken of, the calling of the ministers in the reformed churches, is proved to bee according to the Word of God. Imprimatur, Ja: Cranford.</title>
            <author>M. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A594A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E350_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861623</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159835</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E350[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An admonition given unto Mr. Saltmarsh: wherein his great sinne in writing those pamphlets intituled, A new quære, Smoak in the temple, Groanes for liberty, &amp;c. is plainly laid open before him, and charged upon his conscience. Where also among other things spoken of, the calling of the ministers in the reformed churches, is proved to bee according to the Word of God. Imprimatur, Ja: Cranford.</title>
                  <author>M. W.</author>
                  <author>J. D.</author>
                  <author>S. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 17, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by John Dever &amp; Robert Ibbitson, for Ralph Smith, and are to bee sold at his shop at the signe of the Bible in Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: M.W. J.D. S.B.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug 17".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saltmarsh, John, d. 1647 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADMONITION GIVEN Unto M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>SALT MARSH:</hi> WHEREIN His great Sinne in writing thoſe Pamphlets Intituled, <hi>A New Quaere, Smoak in the Temple, Groanes for Liberty, &amp;c.</hi> Is plainly laid open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and charged upon his Conſcience. Where alſo among other things ſpoken of, the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Miniſters in the Reformed Churches, is proved to bee according to the Word of God.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 TIM. 3.7.</bibl>
               <p>Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the Truth.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 PET. 2.18, 19.</bibl>
               <p>For when they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, they allure through the luſts of the fleſh, through much wantonneſſe, thoſe that were clean eſcaped from them who live in errour. While they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption: for of whom a man is overcome, of the ſame is he brought in bondage.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cypriani Epiſtol.</hi> 52. <hi>Antoniano Fratri.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quòd verò ad Novatiani perſonam attinet (frater Chariſſime) de quo deſideraſti tibi ſcribi quam haereſim introduxiſſet, ſcias nos primo in loco nec curioſos eſſe debere, quid ille doceat, cum foris doceat. Quiſquis ille eſt, &amp; qualiſcunque eſt, Chriſtianus non eſt, qui in Chriſti Eccleſia non eſt. Jactet ſe licèt, &amp; Philoſophiam, vel eloquentiam ſuam ſuperbis vocibus praedicet; qui nec fraternam charitatem, nec Eccleſiaſticam unitatem tenuit, etiam quod prius fuerat amiſit.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed> Ja: Cranford.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>John Dever</hi> &amp; <hi>Robert Ibbitſon,</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Bible in Cornhill. MDCXLVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:159835:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159835:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE occaſion of Printing this following Diſcourſe is this: The Reverend and learned Authour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the comming forth and peruſall of ſome of <hi>Mr. Saltmarſhes</hi> Pamphlets, being much offended and grieved at them; ſent him in a private way this <hi>Admonition,</hi> taking ſpeciall care, that as it ſhould ſafely come to his hands, ſo to let him have notice where hee might return an <hi>Anſwer</hi> back to the Authour, if hee had pleaſed: Now the Authour having waited almoſt foure Moneths for an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> from <hi>Mr. Saltmarſh,</hi> and hearing nothing from him, but on the contrary, ſince hee ſent him this <hi>Admonition, Mr. Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſh,</hi> going on in Printing other things of the like nature, as a Book Intituled <hi>Reaſons for love, unity, and Peace,</hi> with preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Anſwers to <hi>Mr. Gataker, Mr. Ley, Mr. Edwards, Mr. W.</hi> 'tis thought fit to make publick this private <hi>Admonition,</hi> which had it done any good upon him, and brought him to repentance, had never been publiſhed to the world: But thoſe who ſin openly, and being admoniſhed, goe on yet more, ought to bee rebuked before all, that others may fear and learn; And if this publick Reproofe does <hi>Mr. Saltmarſh</hi> no good neither, hee may expect to bee more ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt with, that hee may learn not to blaſpheme.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159835:3"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION GIVEN UNTO MASTER <hi>Saltmarſh.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Maſter Saltmarſh,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I have no acquaintance with your perſon, yet by ſome of your writings, I thinke I can diſcerne ſomewhat of the frame of your Spirit; and though I cannot well conjecture what uſe you will make of that which I purpoſe to expreſſe towards you in love to your Soule; yet I thinke it my dutie at this time, in this manner to admoniſh you, that ſinne may not reſt upon. You know the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our God doth oblige me to this, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.17. And our Saviour doth confirme the ſame in caſes of offence betweene brethren. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. Now I muſt declare unto you in true ſimplicitie, that your wayes of dealing with your Brethren are very offenſive unto me; and I conceive that you are bound in Conſcience, to give me ſome ſatisfaction in that which I ſhall propoſe unto you; either by acknowledging and mending the dangerous error of your wayes; or elſe by rectifying my judgement in the apprehenſion which I have of it.</p>
            <p>The thing then is this, that finding you a Preacher of the Goſpell as you call your ſelfe; and meddling with the controverſies of the time about Church-Government to give Counſell therein to the State what to doe; you follow no Rule of edification, but venture boldly upon all the Wayes of deſtruction, and ſavour nothing of Charitie; in dealing with your Brethren of the Miniſtery; but endevour to make them every way contemptible unto the world by injurious and falſe aſperſions; and to provoke their Spirits to invitation and diſputes againſt you, by a diſorderly &amp; quarrelſome way of writing againſt them. I take no delight (God is my witnes) as you ſeeme to do (in your publicke Writings, with a kind of inſultation over a whole Aſſembly of Divines); to lay this charge (in a private way) upon you; but it is a grief to me to expreſſe it, that I ſhould finde any that cals
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159835:3"/>
himſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpell of Chriſt, lyable unto ſuch faults; and ſo far out of the way, which Chriſts Spirit (the anointing which you ſo much ſpeake of) doth teach his true Diſciples to walke in. Well then, that I may eaſe my ſelfe upon you, of the griefe which you have occaſioned, to the end that the Lord may be mercifull unto you, to incline you (if it be poſſible) to take away the cauſe therof; I ſhall truly and faithfully let you ſee whence it doth ariſe, and how your procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings have begotten it in me.</p>
            <p>I have ſeene heretofore a litle Tract of yours which you call a New Quaere concerning Church-Government, wherein you endevour to perſwade the State to keepe it in an Unſettlement: that Tract, in the aime which you have in it, and the way you take to inſinvate it, with many fallacies in Divinitie fit to intangle the weake, and with many Principles of corrupt, ſenſuall, and worldly State-Policie, fit to ſtir up and confirme Envie and Pride in the hearts of earthly men that have power in their hands; did not a little ſad my ſpirit, when I read it; &amp; had thoughts to have ſpoken to you about it, when I was at <hi>London;</hi> but the opportunitie was not offered, and ſo I left off the thought of it, chiefly when I found that ſome body anſwered it.</p>
            <p>But now beeing out of <hi>London</hi> I meet in the Country with another Tract, of a far worſe nature, (if worſe may be) then that was; concerning the Divine Right of the Presbyterie, wherof I ſhall ſpeake unto you plainly, and in all true love, my thoughts, if perhaps God may be pleaſed to open your eyes, to ſee the ſnare wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are caught by Satan, to be his inſtrument, to tempt all men, to all manner of diſorders, to diſturbe this diſtracted State, and bring it to Rvine, which I beſeech God in mercy to prevent. For truly the way which you have taken, and wherein you proceed with a great deale of confidence, provoking others to follow you and to anſwer you in the ſame kind; if it ſhould be entertained on all ſides; can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce nothing but the Gall of bitterneſſe, and deſtruction in the end. For if yee bite and devovre one another; yee are in danger to be conſumed one of another ſaith the Apoſtle. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.15. Therefore he is carefull to Teach men, that ſuppoſe they live by the Spirit of Chriſt, to ſet themſelves to walke alſo in the Spirit, from ver. 16. till the end of the Chapter, ſhewing that he who endevours to walke in the Spirit, ſhall not be led away to fullfill the luſts of the fleſh, becauſe ſuch as are Chriſts, have Crucified the fleſh with the affections and luſts, and are not deſirous of vaine glory, by provoking one another, or envying one another; as (in all that I have ſeene of your writings in this kind) you are fully and ſtrongly bent to doe; and that under a kind of pretence of zeale for Religion and Moderation: when as, in effect I meet with none that uſeth more devouring words then you have done; or that applyeth them with more cunning to deceive, and to work miſchiefe in the mindes of men. Pardon theſe expreſſions, they are not words of paſſion to reproach, but of compaſſion to warne you of the Spirit by which you are led;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159835:4"/>
that you may reflect upon your ſelfe, and take heed unto your way; and not excuſe the matter, with colourable pretences. For what although ſome Antagoniſts have ſet themſelves to diſcover the ſhamefull nakedneſſe of your Brethren unto the world; and to grate upon the ſores that are painfull, rather to warne others of a danger, then to recover theſe that are the cauſe of the danger, from the error of their waies? I ſay; what although ſome have done thus; &amp; have not dealt with the men of a diſſenting judgement as with Brethren, overtaken in a fault; to reſtore them in the Spirit of meekneſſe: ſhould you therfore that pretend to be ſpirituall, ſuffer your ſelf to be provoked by them to follow the ſame way of irritation; to increaſe the fewell of wrath; and inflame the Spirits of men whom you judge carnall and deſtitute of the anointing? Suppoſe they deale uncharitably with thoſe that you ſtand for; is it therefore lawfull for you or expedient to the cauſe of Religion, or advantageous for your own aime, to deale as uncharitably with them, or rather more injuriouſly? you that affect ſo much the Spirit, and plead for love; ſhould you be overcome with evill, to recompenſe evill for evill, and not rather ſtudie to overcome it with good? recrimination is no juſt defence; and chiefly with ſuch a kind of reproachfull accuſation as you make uſe of; and in ſuch away of applying it as you are fallen upon: for if your accuſations be not only railings, but falſhoods; and if you apply them to the unſettlement of all mens affections towards each other; namely to ſtagger the weake of all ſides and incenſe the ſtrong of each ſide to their utmoſt endevours of ſtrife; if (I ſay) this be ſo; then let me intreat you to reflect upon your ſelfe, and conſider what uſe Satan makes of your tongue and pen for his endes; for if you are not afraid to write in publicke that which I ſee under your name; I may without uncharitableneſſe, imagine, that your tongue in private will not ſpare to walke through the earth in a more deſperate path, perhaps then I can, or will admit into my thoughts, of him whom I do eſteem a brother, therfore, as to a brother, for whom I am ſollicitous (I ſpeak it in the right of Chriſt) let me intreate you (before I come to the particulars which I purpoſe to lay before you, from your writings) to take heede to your ſpeaking; It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to men of nimble wits, to ſpeak freely, to plot deſignes, and uttering them, to ſet themſelves or others upon the acting thereof; and I am afraid it may be made ſome part of your employment, to worke the diviſions of this State and Church to the height by private contrivements; if your ſpirit in your more ſecret walking, be not otherwiſe affected towards your Brethren, and tempered towards the publike Peace; than it appeareth unto me to be in your publicke counſels and writings: wherof now to diſcharge the grievances which I have againſt you at them (I ſhould have ſaid rather againſt them unto you); I will give you a diſtinct and particular acount; and leſt I ſhould ſeeme to complaine without a cauſe, or take upon me towards you more, then I would have you to doe towards my ſelfe in the like caſe: therefore let this be ſaid once for all all, Curſed be he that doth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159835:4"/>
the worke of the Lord deceitfully: or that under the Colour of Chriſtian love, in ſuch a caſe doth ſeeke any other advantage then the gaining of his Brother to a cleere dutie in the Goſpell. If then I ſhall erre in judgment (for who can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to be without error) I deſire you to rectifie my miſtakes, with the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection whereby I offer my ſelfe now to diſcover your miſtakes unto your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, beſeeching the Lord in mercy to let you ſee the danger of them, for your good, and the preſervation of others that may be endangered by them, and wrought upon to follow your footſteps.</p>
            <p>Firſt it is a grievance to my ſpirit to find a ſpecious promiſe in the title of your Treatiſe, ſtirring up an appetite to taſte of ſome ripe fruit of tendernes, which my Soule deſireth in all theſe Controverſies, when as in the Treatiſe it ſelf, I can finde no cluſter at all of comfort or refreſhment. And therefore I have cauſe to cry out with the Prophet <hi>Mich.</hi> 7. Wo is me for I am as when they have gathered the ſummer frvits as the Grape-gleanings of the Vintage: there is no Cluſter to Eat, the good man is periſhed; they all lye in waite for blood; they hunt every man his neighbour with a net &amp;c. If then you will eaſe me of this griefe I pray you ſhew me where the Brotherly tenderneſſe is, and that ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which Maſter <hi>Bachiler</hi> commends your Treatiſe for. If it be no where but in pag. 8 and 9. where you propound for the Parliament that all ſides may enjoy their libertie in their judgement, as now they doe which is in ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it, with all manner of contrivements to make their practiſe according to their judgement, prevalent againſt each other; if this be all, what the better will the State or Church be for this Counſell? What love will this beget? Will it not rather in the unſettlement of all relations and bands of mutuall edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and of orderly proceedings (which ſhould prevent offences, which beget murmurings and diſputes) leave the Reines looſe unto all men to runne riot one againſt another; and in a Carnall way pleaſing themſelves (as you I conceive have done in this Treatiſe) they will not care whom they doe diſpleaſe. I did truly expect ſome lenitive and mollifying cataplaſme or ointment to abate the inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our paines and ſores; and behold a cold water ſprinkled upon them only on the outſide to make them burne more vehemently and ake more inwardly, &amp; harden the boiles that the corrupt matter may never be purged out. If you had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſed ſome arguments convincingly preſſed home, to provoke men to that love which Chriſt requires in us all, and to that forbearance in love which might tend to the healing of breaches: or if you had propounded ſome equitable wayes of Treating betweene the parties to come to a better underſtanding and reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of differences: or if you had ſhewed how the diſtemperat execeſſes of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate men on all ſides, might be without violent courſes (which may reflect upon the Conſciences of tender &amp; weak ones) taken away; I would have reliſhed ſome ſweetneſſe in your ſpirit, or ſome tenderneſſe towards your Brethren. But in very
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159835:5"/>
deed your ſpirit (if I can ſee any thing in the diſpoſition of ſpirits, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6.) is contrary to the Apoſtolical rule (even there where your tendernes doth lye) puffed up highly for one againſt another &amp; if your concluſion of the Treatiſe, wherin you declare the aime you have in writing ſhould be beleeved aſwell as the title; it wil appeare that the title of tenderneſſe is a meer flouriſh and baite to allure a ſimple ſoule to ſwallow a hooke: for you profeſſe in plaine termes that you write to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke others to ſhew their ſtrength againſt you, as in a matter of high concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and your ſelf beeing a man (forſooth) that regard neither an Univerſity nor a Pulpit; neither a Doctor nor a Teacher of theſe Reformed Churches, as if they were all inferior unto your anointing; becauſe ſome of them have not much more then Art and Habit. What doe you meane by this? Doth this proceed from a ſweete fountaine? Can there be tenderneſſe towards a brother, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out humilitie in ones ſelfe? And can ſuch unſavoury provocations, in ſuch high termes, ſtand with true inward humility? Only by pride commeth contention ſaith, <hi>Salomon Prov.</hi> 13.10. And the Apoſtle <hi>James.</hi> 4. tels us, that warres and fightings come from our luſts; Looke then to your aime, and ſee what it luſteth after; and in what manner your ſpirit doth expreſſe that luſt which it hath; and then tell me from your Conſcience, whether your luſt is not to envy and to ſtrife? And if it be clearely by your own words found ſuch; doe not boaſt too faſt of your anointing; and doe not lye againſt the Truth of your aime with a pretence of tenderneſſe: for though you lay no claime to Arts nor Habits; yet the wiſdome by which you are led in this matter deſcendeth not from above but is earthly and ſenſuall. Which I grieve to ſee, and wiſh that you would lay it to heart to be humbled before God for it, that he may be mercifull unto you, and give you indeed that anointing, which you ſeeme to boaſt of; for not he that commends himſelfe, or can diſcommend others, is praiſe worthy; but hee whom God commends, by giving him the ſpirit of wiſdome unto ſobriety, in thinking of himſelfe, and unto charity, and meekneſſe in dealing with others: which I wiſh you from my heart henceforth.</p>
            <p>The Second Grievance is, the inſulting over your Brethren of the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in your Preface to them; by triumphing over them as Humbled from that height wherein you ſeeme to intimate that they thought themſelves ſet; what doe you here gaine either for their edification or your owne? and by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching them with a fault of going beyond their bounder; I am afraid, as you intend not to heale any thing in them, but to exalt your ſelfe alone, to be equall to them all, in your own imagination; ſo perhaps in depreſſing their eſtimation to the magnitude of your ſelfe; you may have a worldly ende, to pleaſe ſome that ſeeke pretences againſt them. I leave this to the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Conſcience, whether I have not cauſe to ſuſpect ſome ſuch thing, where ſo much of worldly reſpect to greatneſſe, and in order to that, ſuch ſelfe-Love
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159835:5"/>
is expreſſed in ſo high a degree, as to deſpiſe all their judgements in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of your owne. Who is ignorant, that as laying too much weight upon the voyces of Synods or Aſſemblies of men; there hath beene or may be, a Myſtery of Iniquity; but will you deny that there hath not beene or may not be, as great, or a greater Myſtery of iniquitie, in that Spirit, which doth extoll it ſelf above the ſpirit of the Prophets, when it ought to be ſubject thereunto? whereunto if you (who boaſt your ſelf ſo eaſily in vanity) are not in danger to be tempted, I am much deceived: therefore it will be your wiſdome to looke in humilitie to your ſtanding, leſt you be alſo tempted, ſeeing you think that a whole Aſſembly of men, of greater abilities then you ſelfe, may come to fall.</p>
            <p>The Third Grievance to my Spirit is this; that you are not afraid to informe the world of many Untruths to the prejudice of your Brethren, that they may be diſreſpected in their Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>And the Fourth Grievance, is this; that you have a peculiar Artifice in the Application of your accuſations to exaſperate mens ſpirrts with hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Brethren, beyond any man that I have knowne.</p>
            <p>Under theſe two heads I comprehend all the particular Grievances which are in the whole Treatiſe, which is nothing but a buſh of thornes which ſcarſe can be touched any where without a prickle: and if your ſpirit can bring forth none other fruits (which I hope by repentance it may) your end will be ſad; for you that can kindle ſo much fire in other mens ſpirits; muſt needes have a great deale of fewell within your ſelfe, which you will do wiſely to caſt out betimes, leſt you taſte of the fruit of your own doings and your backſliding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove you when it may be too late.</p>
            <p>I ſhall endevour only to point at matters briefly; and to eaſe my ſpirit of the burden which you have laid upon it; I ſhall rectifie your miſtakes; and ſhew what ſhould have beene done for edification in truth; if your aime had beene upright and to gaine your lawfull end if you had followed a commendable courſe:</p>
            <p>Under the third head of grievances, I ranke all the Untruths wherewith you aſperſe your Brethren: and by the untruths I meane all the falſ poſitions in matter of Doctrine, which you father upon them; either as their owne or ſuch as they are bound to make good; and all the falſe Aſſertions which you lay as grounds of truth to be received by all; that they in their Miniſtery may be vilified; and all the injurious inferences whereby you miſreport their meaning, in their Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Houſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Here you tell us that they pretend a Right to the Miniſtery, by vertue of that Ordination only, which is derived by a Perſonall ſucceſſion from Biſhops, and ſo upwards to the Apoſtles without interruption: and from this falſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159835:6"/>
ſuppoſition of your owne, which you father upon them as their poſition, you ſpin out a great many abſurdities, which you will oblige them to make good; or to be guilty of. This is the matter of pag. 1 and 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Then you oppoſe the Nature of their Congregational Elderſhip to their Claſſicall and Synodicall; and upon unſound grounds, which you aſſert as truths; calling the Conſtitution of their Elders, and of the extent of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, into queſtion; you labour to bring a diſreſpect upon them, and this is the matter of pag. 3. and part of pag 4.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe they pretend Art to have ſuch an immediate Call as the Apoſtles had, but have only an ordinary meaſure of gifts, you inferre from thence that they have no right to challenge Church-power to themſelves, or to alledge and apply the Scriptures giving that power to Miniſters, unto themſelves: and this you inſiſt upon, pag. 4. 5. 6.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, You traduce the purpoſe and the ende of the Conſtitution of a Nationall Aſſembly and make it formidable to a State, and no loſſe then Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian. pag. 7.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, your inferences upon the heads of the Petition, are the vileſt and moſt injurious miſrepreſentations of their meaning that any can deviſe; to make them bee thought proud and intending to exalt themſelves above the Parliament, to make them guilty of miſ-interpreting the Nationall Covenant; and to make them wholly dependent in all their Adminiſtrations upon the State, or elſe to be thought abſurd in petitioning the removall of the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, and this is the ſubſtance of your pag. 11, 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are nothing elſe but a maſſe of Untruths, and falſe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of matters tending onely to ſtagger the Simpler ſort and to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the enemies either of that Church-Conſtitution; or elſe of all Religion that by the diſſolution of that frame of Government they may bee able to ſinne without Controll, and doe what they will,</p>
            <p>Now that any who cals himſelfe a Preacher of the Goſpell, ſhould ſet himſelfe thus to tradvce theſe whom hee cals Brethren: to the ende that their Miniſterie may become contemptible, is a ſad matter unto me: both in reſpect of the Goſpell which thereby is made unprofitable unto many: and in reſpect of theſe that are wronged, and him that doth the wrong. But that I may not ſeeme to delight ſo much in the aggravating of wrongs as in the rectifying of them: I will Charitably ſuppoſe that you have erred partly through ignorance; and partly through heat of paſſion in all theſe miſ-repreſentations of matters: and not againſt the light of your Conſcience, and through pure Malice. For although there is a ſpirit of Malignity in our corrupt nature leading us to wreſt things to the worſt ſenſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne thoſe to whom we ſeeke to inſult over: yet I hardly can thinke that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159835:6"/>
any who is not a reprobate and voide of all Conſcience; can wittingly and willingly againſt his owne knowledge ſet himſelfe thus to be injurious unto his Brethren in the profeſſion of the Goſpell; to make them Univerſally odious and deſpicable in the Miniſtery. Therefore I thinke it onely an error of judgement in you heightned with paſſion, to take advantages againſt them, to exalt your ſelfe over them, and make them deſpicable. And to Remedy this evill, I will give you my true ſenſe of theſe thinges which are alledged wrongfully by you to their diſreputation; that your miſtake may bee rectified.</p>
            <p>I ſay then that the Reformed Church in theſe and other parts, which hath received the light of the Goſpell ſince the diſcoverie of Poperie doth hold that the true Ordination of Miniſters doth not depend upon any Perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Succeſſion of Men, but upon the appointment of God: who hath given by the Manifeſtation of his Truth, gifts unto his Church which are to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred therein by the Office of the Presbyterie, which hath a power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate it ſelfe; for the continuance of the worke of the Miniſtery in this world. If then ſince the Apoſtles times there hath beene a Church; that is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of true Beleevers in the world, alwayes extant; (whether viſible or inviſible to the world, that is not materiall; all hold that the Church is alwayes viſible to it ſelfe) wee muſt acknowledge that to that Church the gifts of the Spirit have never beene wanting therein: and if the gifts have never failed, there hath alwayes beene a Power in the Elderſhip of that Church to adminiſter the ſame unto the members thereof; by verue of Gods Commandement. 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 4.10, 11. As every man hath received the gift, even ſo, miniſter the ſame one to another as good Stewards of the manifold grace of God. If any man ſpeake let him ſpeake as the Oracles of God, if any man miniſter, let him doe it as of the abilitie which God giveth. From this Commandement wee learne that God hath alwayes in his Church Stewards of his grace; and that hee doth give unto them an Abilitie to miniſter the ſame. This abilitie is partly inward in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of the gift, partly outward in the propertie of the Office, by which it is to bee adminiſtred unto the Church in an orderly way: and that the orderly way of adminiſtration may not faile in the houſe of God (for God is the God of order and not of Confuſion) no man is to take the Office unto himſelfe, but hee is honoured therewith who is called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by God as <hi>Aaron</hi> was <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.4. Now the power of calling in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way, is by the Office of the Elderſhip in the Church, and not by any Perſonall Succeſſion: For it is the Elderſhip that giveth Ordination by the impoſition of hands. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. and where the Office is eſtabliſhed, it may and ought to bee propagated by theſe that are intruſted therewith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159835:7"/>
towards others that are fit to Adminiſter the ſame unto others alſo that there may be a perpetuall continuance thereof: for ſo the Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. Wee ſay then, that the Lord hath never left the world without ſome true Miniſters of the Word; by their Miniſterie of the Word, Faith hath beene begotten; and with Faith the gifts of the Spirit ſent forth; and where the gifts have beene, the Adminiſtration thereof hath alſo beene by vertue of an Office reſiding in thoſe to whom God doth give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie: if then a Miniſter of the Reformed Church bee called unto an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Right which hee hath unto his Office; hee will give this proof of it: That in a true Church of God, according to his appointment, after tryall, and manifeſtation of his gifts and graces, found fit for edification; hee was called, and by theſe that did Adminiſter in that Church the Office of the Elderſhip, was in an orderly manner ordained and dedicated with Prayer and impoſition of hands unto God, to have a lot and part in his Service: and they juſtly reject from the Societie of that Office all ſuch as come not in by this orderly and ordinary way; nor ought they to admit of any; or acknowledge him to be a Steward of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God, who is not thus called by the Elderſhip of ſome true Church.</p>
            <p>If you knew this to be the true meaning of the Reformed Churches, and did nevertheleſſe runne out upon the Cavills you have in your firſt and ſecond page, you are much to blame; but if you knew it not; you ſhould have made enquiry; and not have condemned your Brethren upon a falſe preſuppoſall: the Miniſters of the Low-Countries and of <hi>France</hi> are not ordained by Biſhops; and none doth queſtion their Calling to the Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>As for the Congregationall, Claſſicall, and Synodicall Presbyteries; if they bee Rightly Conſtituted and met together in the Communion of Saints for their mutuall edification in love, they all ſtand a like by Divine Right; for if the Elderſhip of one ſingle Congregation hath a right from God to determine that which is fit for its owne edification within it ſelfe; it cannot be denyed but the Elderſhips of many Congregations joyned together have the ſame right: whatſoever they have Single; they cannot loſe Conjoyned, but their Right is rather ſtrengthened by their union. And what you ſpeake of a Prudentiall Judicature, is but a Cavill: All Churches have a right from God to judge of all affaires Prudentially for their owne building up in love by the Rules. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26, 40.</p>
            <p>Then to the exception which you make againſt Elders as Conſtituted by the countenance of an Ordinance of Parliament, and not by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Scripture-Rule; I ſay that their conſtitution to bee Officers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159835:7"/>
in the Church is onely from the Apoſtolicall Rule and the Parliament-Ordinance is but an outward accidentall concurrence and helpe to the ſetling of them by the Rule; therefore this is nothing, but a Cavill in like manner. So is alſo that which is called a Pariſhionall Congregation, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Circumſtantiall outward boundary of a certaine number of people, in which a Spirituall Congregation is to bee ſetled according to the Word; and therefore this is another Cavill like unto the former. And as for the Aſſembly in this Extraordinary way of Reformation; it is a neceſſary helpe in the Communion of Saints for Counſell and Advice to maintaine the Unitie of the Spirit amongſt Brethren in the bond of Peace; and their Convocation by the approbation of Parliament, is but acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall to the Right which the Miniſters have to come together to doe things for mutuall edification, and to determine among themſelves their wayes of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly proceeding in love.</p>
            <p>We confeſſe that the Primitive Elders and Apoſtles were immediatly and more eminently qualified, then theſe that are now in place, but wee ſay alſo that the different meaſure of gifts makes no eſſentiall difference in the nature of the Adminiſtration; there is but one Faith, and one Spirit, and one Body, the anointing of all is the ſame; and every member is bound in his place, according to his Office, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4. to ſupply to others that gift for the Adminiſtration whereof <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.16. the whole Body by Chriſts Ordinance and under him is fitly joyned together and compacted: that God may be glorified in all things by Jeſus Chriſt. If wee beleeve in the Word of the Apoſtles, wee have Communion with them, and are bound to follow them in all the Ordinances of worſhip, and of mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all edification. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1, 2. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> were no more priviledged to this than any Company of true beleevers are now; therefore it is but a meere Cavill to tell us, becauſe we have not ſuch a degree of the anointing, that wee may not Adminiſter the Ordinances; according to that degree and meaſure of gifts which wee have: there is a promiſe that if wee be faithfull in little we ſhall bee ſet over much. If wee beleeve truly wee have a right to all the Ordinances by the Word; and all Offices and Officers in their Adminiſtrations, are warranted thereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> edifie their fellow members within themſelves, without any depe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance upon any extrinſecall power: and although they ought to doe this; and to doe it as by the abilitie which God giveth; yet they cannot pretend to any infallibilitie in their Adminiſtrations, whether of Doctrine, of Worſhip, of Government, or of Cenſures, but in humilitie as under the Direction of the Word, they make uſe of their gifts till God bring them to the Stature of a Perfect man in Chriſt; and that they may come to this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159835:8"/>
perfection they ſtand joynted and compacted with their Brethren in the Communion of Saints, and thinke it not ſafe or lawfull for them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynt themſelves, as I underſtand you have done; from ſuch as call upon God out of a pure heart; and are grounded in the ſame Truth of Faith with them, and are united to the ſame God and Father by the ſame Covenant of Grace in Chriſt: from ſuch you have ſeparated your ſelfe, and are now become a Cavillator and wrangler againſt them, ſeeking by all meanes of rayling and falſe imputations to diſturbe their Peace, and make people diſaffected towards them: for which ſinne if you repent not, you will become a wandering Starre, and never ſettle for ever: from which judgement I beſeech the Lord to preſerve you: for I feare that you are on the way of looſing your hold of the Scriptures, aſwell as of the Truth of Love to the Brethren. When men once take a libertie to doe all things that their owne Spirit doth lead them unto by paſſion, and boaſt withall of the Spirit and anointing, and deſpiſe others in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of themſelves; and doe not ſtudy to ſhew from the Scriptures that light which God hath manifeſted unto them for the inſtruction and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of others to recover them with love and meekneſſe from the wayes of error; but inſult over them, and trample upon them for their defamation and deſtruction, (I ſay) when men are thus acted by Satan; they are in a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous condition.</p>
            <p>Concerning a Nationall Aſſembly wee ſay that it hath no power but in matters of Spirituall concernment; and that the Divine Rights which is in all the particular Churches by an aggregation of ſtrength is Contracted in it, and therefore is the true ſupreme Judicature in matters of difference amongſt Brethren: yet according to the Word, and by the Word, and through the manifeſtation of the will of God, the judgement is Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and not otherwiſe: and you but Cavill and play the Polititian to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter States-men, for ſome ends of your owne, when you labour to ſtirre up a jealouſie in the Parliament againſt the Authoritie of a Nationall Aſſembly: their Spheres are ſo farre different in nature, their ends ſo diſtinct, their Principles ſo farre diſtant; and the Manner of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eding in dealing with thoſe that relate unto them, ſo quite oppſit; that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they will not purpoſely goe out of their wayes they cannot entrench <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon one anothers borders of Power, but each is under God immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within it ſelfe, over all its members; and one is mutually ſubordinate to another according to his Will: the Eccleſiaſticall Perſons are under the Civill Judicature in matters of this World; and the Civill Perſons are under the Eccleſiaſticall Judicature in matters of the World to come; but you confound all theſe Relations, and either ignorantly or witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159835:8"/>
for ſome endes, will heede this diſtinction of Powers, committed to each in their ſeverall Adminiſtrations under God; the one for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the other for the outward man, which ought no more to bee at variance in a State then Soule and Body in one and the ſame Man in their facultties and operations upon their diſtinct Objects. Here you ſhew the rayling diſpoſition of your minde, when you parallel the Nationall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of all the Reformed Churches (againſt all evident experience of their behaviour to the contrary; and againſt the cleere light of their Doctrine whereby they Challenge no intereſt in the Government of worldly matters) with the Papal and Antichriſtian Power, which hath exalted it ſelfe above all that is called God on Earth, and in Heaven alſo.</p>
            <p>The inferences which you make upon their Petition are ſuch as truly deſerve none other obſervation but this; that it is an untruth which you ſay at the beginning of every inference; namely that you may inferre from their words that which you doe inferre, for I ſay that you may not make evill inferences and miſconſtructions of any mans meaning from his words; if they can beare any better ſenſe then you can put upon them to his prejudice, may you bee injurious and uncharitable to your Brethren? May you accuſe them of wicked intentions againſt their cleare profeſſions? if you may doe this, what may you not doe? I pray you looke to your ſelfe what liberty you take: you preſſed to bee in a Spirituall liberty; but looke now whether in uſing your libertie thus, you give not an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to your fleſh, to ſow the ſeede of diviſions of Complaints of murmurings and diſputes, and of all evill affections againſt your Brethren.</p>
            <p>Therefore the laſt grievance which I ſhall offer unto you to Conſider in your way, is, the Artifice which you uſe to exaſperate the Spirits of men by a miſconſtruction even of the beſt things which are in them to the worſt ſenſe; with ſo much boldneſſe and varietie of applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in ſuch a Tautologicall way to beate it upon the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Earthly men; and to intricate the thoughts of the ſimple, that it is a great matter of ſorrow, to ſee you ſo buſie in a perverſe zeale to ſowe diſſenſion amongſt Brethren. You builde upon your own falſe ſuppoſalls and inferences, a kinde of Method to inſtruct people in the wayes of oppoſition; wherein It will not trace you becauſe it is tedious and unprofitable, and needleſſe to ſhew you all the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full windligs of your Spirit; to which you give an unlimited libertie to intangle men by fallacies. I ſhall rather repreſent unto you what in your caſe if you had beene zealous for the Truth and not for decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and leading men out of the way; you ſhould have done. Hearken
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159835:9"/>
now then, and conſider, you that talke ſo much of Truth. All The Truth which wee ſhould aime at, and beare witneſſe unto, one towards another; is either of Doctrine or Practiſe: The Truth of Doctrine is the Teſtimony of the Word and Spirit, whereby God hath revealed himſelfe and the things belonging to Chriſt and his Kingdome, unto us: that by this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge wee might receive all things pertaining to life, and to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The Truth of Practiſe is that upright and ſincere dealing with others in God for their good according to our beſt knowledge of the things which wee would deſire to have from them in the ſame kinde. The meanes to make this Truth of both kindes effectually profitable to our ſelves and others, is to endevour that which the Apoſtle exhorts us unto, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15. Namely <hi>to ſpeake the Truth in Love;</hi> and the effect of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour will bee, that which hee doth promiſe, there ſhall follow thereupon, Namely <hi>to grow up in all things into him, who is the Head, even Chriſt.</hi> Thus then whether it bee a matter of Doctrine or of Practiſe whereunto we are to beare witneſſe; if we deſire thereby to grow up within our ſelves, or to build up others into Chriſt (which is the onely warrantable aime wee can have) wee muſt apply our mindes to ſpeake the Truth in Love, and to doe the Truth in Love; For the originall words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> containe the ſenſe of both in one expreſſion. If then this is the Rule by which wee ſhould walke in all things, that wee may approve our Conſciences to God as his true ſervants, and enjoy Chriſt by walking after his Spirit in all things: then wee muſt never ſuffer any humane and worldly aimes to ſway our thoughts, to ſpeake or act, that which may tend onely to ſatisfie our own or other peoples humours; but before wee undertake a buſineſſe towards others, whether the concernment be private or publicke, we ſhould ſettle the affections of Truth, and diſcerne the way of uttering them in Love, to gaine theſe with whom wee deale, to ſome dutie of godlineſſe, wherein they and wee may grow up in Chriſt. Now then to apply this Spirituall Method of proceeding to your Caſe, let us State the Queſtion which you make, and conſider how you ſhould, and I would have proceeded, if it had beene my Caſe; to deſire a Reſolution for my ſelfe or others in it.</p>
            <p>The Queſtion is Concerning the Divine Right of the Prebyteriall Churches to judge themſelves of the ſcandalls of their Members according to the Word of God; whether yea or no it doth belong unto them? I would have ſet downe this Quaere diſtinctly, as a Doubt: and then would have ſought out a way, to reſolve my ſelfe without partialitie onely for love to the Truth in it: and to this effect I would have lookt upon the frame and conſtitution, with the Doctrine and Practiſe of the Churches which are called Presbyteriall: and ſet downe truly all that I ſhould have found ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159835:9"/>
materiall in them for their owne beeing; or diſtinctively obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable to difference them from other Churches. Then in the ſecond place I would have made enquirie of their true meaning of that which they call a <hi>Scandall in a Member,</hi> and of that which is called <hi>Judging within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> of Scandalls. And laſtly of that which is called a <hi>Divine Right, whereunto</hi> they pretend in this act of judging, and when I ſhould have ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied my ſelfe in this enquirie ſo farre as I could attaine; if then I had judged them to bee in an error either of Doctrine or Practiſe hurtfull to the Kingdome of Chriſt, and to their owne and others intereſt therein; I would have taken a reſolution to deale with them in Truth and ſincerity to reclaime them from that error; and anſwerable to ſuch a reſolution, would have declared unto them my aime in dealing with them; and deſired them to weigh, and ſeriouſly to conſider the doubts which I had concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Pretence of a Divine Right, perſwading them to lay downe the plea thereof. And if in their ordinarie Practiſes to maintaine and get poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of this Right I ſhould have obſerved things deſtructive to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpell of Peace, or to the edification and true libertie of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I would with all zeale and true affection have warned them of the danger, and laying the fault cleerly before them on the one ſide, I ſhould have laboured to cauſe them to ſee the dutie which God requireth of them on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and ſo commended them to the Grace of God; having diſcharged my Conſcience towards them. And thus I have at this time diſcharged my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards you: and I have endevoured to walke within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of my Rule in conſidering you and your wayes, and in dealing with you freely and roundly to pull you out of the fire; ſo I ſhall deſire you to deale with mee by the ſame Rule, and if in this matter of griefe, which your unruly dealing hath occaſioned; I have exceeded in a Word of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure too ſharply heere or there perhaps; I ſhall deſire you not to take it in the worſt ſenſe: I have not much time to ſpare from ſome other employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and therefore in the griefe of ſpirit, and beeing in haſte with-all to diſpatch theſe thoughts unto you; I may eaſilie have failed in ſome words: for in many things wee faile all, ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> 3. (not excluding himſelfe) and he that offendeth not in a word, hee is a perfect man; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I muſt plead for a Charitable conſtruction of all my expreſſions; and the rather, becauſe the former part of this letter to you is alreadie ſent to <hi>London,</hi> before I could deliberatly review it, as I might have done if time would have given me leave; nor have I any Copy of that which is gone, which is at leaſt three parts of foure; but I hope the friend to whom it is ſent will keepe a Copy thereof for mee; and will not (I know) doe any thing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159835:10"/>
in the divulging of theſe things to your prejudice: but will faithfully concurre with me in this aime of your edification.</p>
            <p>I pray you look not upon matters in appearance, but look upon them in the Truth: ſet your ſelfe to bee a Servant of the Truth, in Love; by provoking all men unto the love which Chriſt requireth of us; and not to the wrath which our paſſions (by conceiving of things according to their worſt conſtruction) may waken in others; to trouble them and increaſe their ſin: Remember, that the wrath of man doth not fulfill the righteouſneſſe of God: and if your zeale bee a wrathfull zeale rather to finde out faults, and make them odious, then to amend and heale the breaches of our ſpirits; you will bee ſo far from doing good to thoſe with whom you deale, that you will not onely make them leſſe corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible; but you will make your own ſide worſe, by being out of all patience againſt them: for the Method that you follow, as it is pleaſing to the fancy of fleſh and blood; ſo it cannot but work upon thoſe that are ignorantly zealous, (and that give credit unto your aſſertions) moſt violent and diſtempered com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, againſt thoſe whom they imagine to bee ſo hatefull to God; and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the publick and to all their Brethren, as you make them, and if they bee not ſo hatefull indeed as you make them; what judgement, you may expect; and reward, for judging of others unjuſtly, in the day of Accounts; I leave you to conſider: It is very good to minde often that wee ſhall give an account of all our idle words: and that by our words wee ſhall bee judged: and by our words wee ſhall bee condemned. The Lord teach us his feare in all things, and grant, that before all keeping, wee may keep the wayes of our heart from double aimes in ſpirituall matters: not to look a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſquint unto the worldly deſignes of States, or great-Ones; to ſerve their turnes with our indevours. Doe not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire who I am, you may come to know mee in due time; look upon mee, as I doe upon you, in your Writings; I never ſaw your face to my knowledge, and perhaps you will never ſee mine: I deſire to know no body after the fleſh; take you onely notice of that which I am to you in the ſpirit,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend, for Chriſts ſake, willing to ſerve you, <hi>M.W. J.D. S.B.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aprill 24. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:159835:10"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF you ſhall think fit to return any Anſwer to theſe things, which I have offered to your conſideration; you may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe your Letter with the letters which expreſſe my name, in the fore-going ſubſcription; and you may bee pleaſed to ſend it to the place, which hee that doth bring this unto you, ſhall name: and from thence it will bee ſafely addreſſed to mee: Thus again, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, as before, <hi>M.W. I.D. S.B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
